Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Ernie O'Malley Papers
Bulk, 1920-1957
1643-2010 (bulk 1920-1957)
AIA.060
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
28.25 linear feet (39 boxes)
The collection contains manuscript works of Ernie O'Malley, and others, correspondence, both personal and business-related, nationalist material including military training manuals, diaries, clippings, and financial and legal material. Of special interest are drafts and publicity related to several of O'Malley's works including On Another Man's Wound, The Singing Flame (published in the U.S. as Army without Banners), Raids and Rallies and several poems. Of note is a series devoted to works and correspondence between O’Malley and the artist Jack B. Yeats. Material detailing O'Malley's interest in art and purchases of art comprise a series entitle Art Materials. A series of subject files includes material collected by and about O'Malley by his son Cormac O'Malley.
O'Malley, Cormac K. H.
O'Malley, Ernie, 1897-1957
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into 15 series. Series are arranged either alphabetically or chronologically. A folder index is provided at the beginning of each series.
Series I. Works, 1924-1956, undated
Series II. Correspondence: Incoming, 1922-1956
Series III. Correspondence: Outgoing, 1922-1956
Series IV. Correspondence: Family, 1914-1957
Series V. Personal, 1912-2006
Series VI. Legal, 1921-1957
Series VII. Financial, 1935-1957
Series VIII. Nationalist Materials, 1643-1966, undated
Series IX. Jack B. Yeats, 1904-1980
Series X. Diaries, Notes and Research, 1922-1963
Series XI. Clippings and Publicity, 1895-2002
Series XII. Arts Material, 1918-1955
Series XIII. Chronology Files, 1920-1957
Series XIV. Subject Files, 1922-2008
Serie XV. Printed Ephemera, 1789-1950
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Provenance
The collection was donated to Tamiment library in December 2010 by Cormac O'Malley, son of Ernie O'Malley.
Historical/Biographical Note
Ernie O'Malley was an Irish Republican Army officer during the Irish War of Independence of 1919-1921 and a senior commander of the anti-treaty IRA during the Irish Civil War, 1922-1923. O'Malley wrote four books, On Another Man's Wound, The Singing Flame, Raids and Rallies, Sean Connolly of Longford in addition to numerous poems, short stories, articles and reviews. A renaissance man, O'Malley was interested in art, archaeology, folklore, photography, literature and history, but also in the lives of those he fought with during the Irish Independence movement. In the 1950s he interviewed over 450 survivors of those he had fought along with, and these interviews were the basis for the episodes covered in his Raids and Rallies and Sean Connolly. Some notes on these interviews are included in the collection [though the majority of the notesboks are at the UCD Archives], along with his other published and unpublished works (poems, short stories, reviews and essays), correspondence, financial and legal documents, dairies and notebooks, subject files and clippings.
O'Malley was studying medicine at University College Dublin in 1916 when the Easter Rising took place. Although not a nationalist at the time, O’Malley having been invited by some friends to help defend Trinity College, Dublin in case the Irish Volunteers attempted to take it over, he decided his sympathies were with the rebels and thus began his military career. When he went on the run in 1917, he was asked by Michael Collins to organize IRA brigade units throughout rural Ireland and later as a Commandant General, at age 24, he commanded the IRA's Second Southern Division in Munster with 7,000 men. O’Malley was captured twice during his military career, the first time by the British in Kilkenny in December 1920 after which he was interrogated and badly beaten. With the threat of execution imminent he, and two other IRA men, escaped from Kilmainham Jail on February 14, 1921. At this arrest he had identified himself as 'Bernard Stewart' and when he escaped, his true identity was still unknown. O'Malley was captured a second time on November 4, 1922 after a shoot-out with Free State troops in a house in Dublin. Critically wounded, he managed to survive prison for almost two years and 41 days on hunger strike before finally being released in mid-1924. Although still not well, he decided to seek a warmer climate hoping to recover both physically and spiritually and traveled in Europe spending time hiking in the Pyrannes, museum hopping and self-studying art and architecture while constantly writing. After returning to medical studies in Dublin for 1926-28, he was asked to go with Frank Aiken to the United States by Eamon de Valera to raise funds for the establishment of a new ‘independent’ newspaper, The Irish Press. His notes and impressions of these journeys, 1928-1935, are included in the collection in Notebook Series and elsewhere in the Correspondence Series. O’Malley settled in Taos and Santa Fe, New Mexico for 1929-1932 and there met many artists and writers and occasionally lectured on modern Irish history and literature while writing his memoirs. He also traveled extensively in Mexico in 1931 for nine months following his interests in folklore, archaeology, modern Mexican art and teaching, - all the while writing.
In 1932 during the height of the Depression, O’Mally returned to New York to finish and publish his memoir, On Another Man’s Wound. With introductions from Paul Strand, met many of the city’s literary, theatre and artistic circles. He continued to write articles, poems and short stories, but only his poems were published. The manuscript for his memoir was rejected many times. In the meantime with the change in government in Ireland, he became eligible for a pension for his military service and wounds, and this led to his return to Ireland to secure his pension. While in New York he also met his future wife here, Helen Hooker, a sculptor and photographer, who had travelled extensively in Europe and Russia. Helen was the daughter of Elon Huntington Hooker, a wealthy businessman and founder of Hooker Electrochemical Company from Greenwich, Connecticut. When he returned to Ireland in 1935 she followed him. They married on September 27, 1935, and he returned to medical school. The couple settled initially in Dublin and later in County Mayo, Ireland, on a farm. O’Malley continued writing and Helen continued her sculpture, photography and theatre interests. The couple had three children. After the marriage broke down in the late 1940s and Helen effectively returned to the United States, she ‘kidnapped’ two of the children, Cathal and Etain, and brought then to America where she initiated divorce proceedings in 1950. O’Malley’s youngest son, Cormac, remained with his father. The divorce was finalized in 1952. After being in poor health for several years Ernie O’Malley died in 1957 in Dublin.
During his lifetime, O’Malley published one critically acclaimed work about his experiences in the Irish War for Independence: On Another Man’s Wound. His second volume, The Singing Flame, covering the Civil War was only published posthumously. O'Malley had published a series of articles in The Sunday Press in 1955-56, describing his and other fighters' experiences, using the interviews he had conducted with former IRA men, and these were also published after his death as Raids and Rallies. The collection includes this serialization as well as reviews and publicity on these works and others in the Clippings and Publicity Series.
In 1991, Prisoners: The Civil War Letters of Ernie O'Malley was published by his son Cormac and Richard English, the latter who also went on to write his biography, Ernie O’Malley: IRA Intellectual in 1998. In 2007, Cormac edited and published N o Surrender Here!The Civil War Papers of Ernie O’Malley, 1922-1924, being a compilation of anti-Treaty military communications and his father’s letters from prison during the Civil War. Cormac also edited and published Rising-Out: Sean Connolly of Longford, 1890-1921 in 2007. Broken Landscapes: Selected Letters of Ernie O'Malley, 1924-1957, also co-edited by Cormac and Nicholas Allen is being published in 2011.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Related materials include:
James J. Comerford Papers AIA 010
Cormac O'Malley Papers AIA 019
Archives of Irish American Pamphlet Collection AIA 047
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ernie O'Malley reflect his varied interests and reveal a complicated intellectual. Interviews with veterans of the War of Independence and Irish Civil War can be found in Series XIII. Nationalist Materials as well as military manuals. Numerous art catalogs, clippings, research and corrspondence to and from artists as well as many works of poetry are found throughout the series, detailing O'Malley's love of art and literature. Essays, articles, poetry, short stories, drawings and manuscrips of his major works are included. Correspondence makes up another signficant part of the collection with the writings of O'Malley comprising another. Other writings by O'Malley can be found in Series X. Diaries, Notes, and Research.
Series I. Works contains two subseries. Subseries IA. Ernie O'Malley comprises literary manuscripts, articles, book reviews, essays, short stories, poetry, notes, drawings and speeches written or created by Ernie O'Malley between the years of 1926 and 1956. Published and unpublished works, manuscript drafts, reprints and photocopies are represented. A considerable amount of O'Malley's works were written during his travels throughout the United States and Mexico between 1928 and 1935. A substantial portion of his literary output centers on his homeland, his military experiences during both the Irish War of Independence and Civil War, early Christian art in Ireland and Irish artists. Other works reflect his interest in art, poetry and a variety of other topics. Materials within the Works series are manuscript and/or typescript and are so indicated on the corresponding folder.
Works by other authors are found in Subseries IB. Other Writers. Material is listed by author and title of the work and organized alphabetically. Throughout his life O'Malley collected ballads and poetry written by others. While most of these materials were either transcribed by O'Malley himself or typed for his personal reference or use, several of the items are clippings or printed materials sent to him by friends and colleagues. Poets within this series include both American and European poets such as Lascelles Abercrombie, Hart Crane, Emily Dickinson, Horace Gregory, James Joyce, Stanley Kunitz, Ezra Pound, Seamus O'Sullivan, John Millington Synge and numerous others. Additional works by others include articles, plays and essays sent to O'Malley for his consideration, review and comment.
For additional materials relating to the works and literary output of Ernie O'Malley see Series 10: Diaries, Notebooks and Research.
Series II. Correspondence: Incoming was originally divided into American and Non-American correspondents but these have been combined into one set of incoming correspondence. The separate indices for these listings are included in the index folder for the series. Files are arranged alphabetically by surname.
Included are letters, telegrams, greeting cards and postcards sent to Ernie O'Malley between the years of 1922 and 1956. The correspondence in this series is of a personal nature, detailing O'Malley's friendships and associations, as well as a business nature documenting O'Malley's dealings with publishers, solicitors, and government agencies. Throughout the course of his life O'Malley maintained friendships with notable artists, poets and writers in both Ireland and the United States. Of special interest are the postcards and letters sent to O'Malley while he was imprisoned at Kilmainham Jail and Curragh Camp during the Irish Civil War in 1923 and 1924.
A limited number of items in this series are photocopies received from various universities, institutions, or private family collections at the request of Cormac O'Malley, Ernie O'Malley's youngest son. Throughout the course of research on his father Cormac O'Malley also transcribed a considerable number of the letters written by Ernie O'Malley. Those transcriptions have been included with the original or photocopy when available.
Letters from Ernie O'Malley to friends, associates, artists, editors, professors, military comrades, government agencies, solicitors, and other correspondents in Ireland and the United States between the years of 1922 and 1956 comprise Series III. Correspondence: Outgoing. Topics in this series range broadly from general greetings to business dealings. Many of the letters provide insight into O'Malley's ailments and failing health resulting from injuries he sustained during his military career. Of special interest are letters O'Malley wrote concerning his work with the Irish Press in the United States and the status of his pension from the Irish government, and transcriptions of letters from O'Malley to Monsignor John Hagan (1925-1926) with O'Malley using the alias, Cecil Smyth-Howard. A substantial number of items in this series are photocopies received from various universities and institutions, at the request of Cormac O'Malley, Ernie O'Malley's youngest son. Throughout the course of research on his father Cormac O'Malley also transcribed a considerable number of the letters written by Ernie O'Malley. Those transcriptions have been included with the original or photocopy when available. See the accompanying index for a complete listing of correspondents indicating where originals are currently held, as well as, the volume of correspondence associated with each correspondent.
Series IV. Correspondence: Family includes incoming and outgoing correspondence between Ernie O'Malley and members of his family including his mother, siblings, children, wife, in-laws, cousins and others. Also included in this series are letters from family members that were neither addressed to nor written by O'Malley. As in the other Correspondence Series, numerous photocopies of originals exist within this series.
Address books, memberships, book slips, inventories, lists, invitations, announcements, school records, memorabilia and other miscellaneous materials covering various events in Ernie O'Malley's life make up Series V. Personal. Throughout the course of his life O'Malley, an avid reader, acquired a vast and diverse personal library. Due to financial hardships during the late 1940s and early 1950s O'Malley was forced to sell a substantial portion of books from his personal library. Card catalogs and inventories in this series reflect the many changes in his personal collection of books before and following the sale. Of special interest is a collection of book slips from the National Library of Ireland, New York Public Library and Newberry Library in Chicago, Illinois documenting the hundreds of books O'Malley read or checked out from each institution during the 1930s. Series is arranged alphabetically by type, generally.
Series VI. Legal consists of legal documents and clippings relating to Ernie O'Malley between the years 1923-1957. Most materials in this series relate to the legal proceedings in 1950 between O'Malley and his estranged wife, Helen Hooker O'Malley. Also included are clippings documenting the libel lawsuit and settlement between Joseph O'Doherty and Ernie O'Malley following O'Malley's publication of On Another Man's Wound. Many of the official legal documents in this series are photocopies received from the High Court of Justice in Dublin, Ireland.
Series VII. Financial contains invoices, receipts, bills and correspondence from purveyors and businesses pertaining to items bought for the O'Malley household, including food, clothing, electricity, household furnishings, car repairs and books and publications. The material provides a unique and intimate look into the personal life of the O'Malley family.
Series VIII. Nationalistic Materials includes newspaper clippings, booklets, notes, pamphlets, military training manuals, reports, memorandums, photographs and other printed matter relating to the nationalist movement in Ireland. Drawn to the nationalist cause in midst of the Easter Rising in 1916, O'Malley later joined the Irish Republican Army and became a key figure in the War of Independence and Irish Civil War. Items in this series provide details of O'Malley's military career, as well as, insight into the publications and propaganda that powered the nationalist movement throughout Ireland. Also included in this series are official reports and memoranda issued by Oglaigh na hEireann, otherwise known as the Irish Republican Army. Of special interest in this series are a few items relating to O'Malley's interviews with veterans of the War of Independence and Civil War. Beginning in the early 1940s, O'Malley embarked on an ambitious effort to document first-hand accounts of both wars and as a result, hand-recorded approximately 450 interviews with his former military comrades. Most items relating to his military interviews were placed in the archives of University College Dublin in 1974; however, a limited amount of materials pertaining to the interviews remain in this series.
Materials in this series are in two groups: military training manuals arranged chronologically and printed material arranged alphabetically.
Series IX. Jack B. Yeats comprises correspondence, articles, clippings, invitations, cancelled checks, receipts, notes, exhibition catalogs, stamps and photographs collected by Ernie O'Malley relating to Jack B. Yeats, as well as, items relating to Yeats' father, John B. Yeats, and brother, William Butler Yeats. Items in this series are of both a personal and professional nature. O'Malley and Jack B. Yeats met in Ireland during the 1930s and developed a friendship that lasted until their deaths in 1957. In addition to being a patron of Yeats' artwork, O'Malley served on the Jack B. Yeats National Loan Exhibition Committee and authored the introduction for the exhibition's catalog in 1945. Throughout the course of their friendship Yeats gifted O'Malley various pencil sketches and writings by John B. Yeats, in addition to several letters written by the elder Yeats to his other son, William Butler Yeats. Other items include Yeats materials collected by Ernie O'Malley's son, Cormac O'Malley.
Series X. Diaries, Notes and Research consists of journals, notebooks, diaries, loose notes and research by Ernie O'Malley contextualizing his literary output and body of work. Items in this series reflect the commentary, criticisms, critiques and general notes taken by O'Malley on a variety of topics including art, literature, poetry and history, and provide insight into his research methodology and writing process. Most notebooks in this series are untitled, however, some notebooks bear the letters "P" indicating painting, or "I" for Ireland. Of special interest in this series are O'Malley's diaries from his travels in the United States and Mexico, and notebooks relating to his military career. See the accompanying index for an itemized listing, description and full summary of each notebook in this series. Additional notebooks and notes may be found in Series 1: Works and Series 12: Art Materials.
The series is arranged chronologically, with Notes arranged alphabetically by subject and filed at the end of the series.
Series XI. Clippings and Publicity includes newspaper clippings, book reviews, magazine features, advertisements, book covers and correspondence relating to Ernie O'Malley, his literary output and posthumous publications. Many of the clippings in this series were collected by O'Malley and reflect his general interests in art, literature, poetry, theatre and current affairs. Clippings also relate to international affairs and historic events including the Second World War, Spanish Civil War and Anglo-Irish relations. O'Malley collected articles of interest from both American and European newspapers including, The New York Times, Irish Independent and Irish Press. This series also contains clippings detailing O'Malley's funeral, as well as, book reviews and other items pertaining to the publication of On Another Man's Wound and its German translation, Rebellen en Irlande. Additional items in this series relate to the publicity of books published after his death by O'Malley's son Cormac O'Malley and Richard English including Prisoners: The Civil War Letters of Ernie O'Malley and Richard English's Ernie O'Malley: IRA Intellectual.
The series is arranged chronologically.
The notebooks, notes, works, lectures, clippings, magazine articles, photographs, postcards, reprints of artwork, brochures, sketches, exhibition catalogues, theatre programs and printed materials in Series XII. Arts Materials reflect O'Malley's interest in painting, sculpture, architecture, archeology, music and theatre throughout Europe, Mexico and the United States. Many of the clippings, magazine articles and reprints were collected by O'Malley as research for his articles and essays on painting, sculpture, archeology, architecture and other related topics. A substantial number of art catalogues and theatre programs were deposited at University College Dublin by O'Malley's son, Cormac O'Malley, in 1974. Photocopies of the aforementioned items remain in this series, along with nearly 50 original art catalogues and theatre programs. Also included in this series are more than 200 copies of photographs taken by O'Malley, Helen Hooker O'Malley and others from Mexico and Ireland. Of special interest are notes taken by O'Malley during a series of interviews he conducted with organizers of the Irish Exhibition of Living Art during the 1940s. O'Malley's interest in art criticism encouraged him to embark on series of interviews with some of Ireland's most prominent modern artists including, Evie Hone, Jack Hanlon, Louis le Brocquy, Norah McGuinness, Nano Reid and many others. Works by other authors are filed at the end of this series.
Series XIII. Chron[ology] Files contains art exhibition catalogues, theatre programs, clippings, bills, receipts, correspondence, graphic materials and printed matter collected by Ernie O'Malley and organized chronologically by his son, Cormac O'Malley. Items in this series document his routine activities, and some expenses, as well as, many of friends and associates. A number of the items in this series are photocopies of originals housed elsewhere in the collection, but left here for handy chronological reference.